Guide to the Picture File, 1700s-1980s and undated RL.01025
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Picture File
1700s-1970s and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01025
50 Linear Feet
The Picture File was created by the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a vertical file from the 1950s to the 1980s. Images were separated from manuscript collections as well as added individually from other sources. The Picture File is a large and diverse collection of visual materials ranging from the 17th through the 20th centuries.
Arrangement
The collection has been sorted into series: Subjects, Geographic, Socialist Party Records, and People. Two additional series -- Negatives and Stereographs -- were separated from the main collection based on format and housing concerns.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Picture File was created by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1950 and 2019 as a vertical file of images from across library collections.
Related Materials
See also: the History of Medicine Picture File, held by Rubenstein Library.
Collection Overview
The Picture File is a large and diverse collection of visual materials ranging from the 17th through the 20th centuries. The bulk of the images in the collection date from the early 1800s through the 1950s. Formats represented include black and white photographic prints; cartes de visite, cabinet cards and other albumen prints; tintypes and daguerreotypes; engravings and lithographs; political cartoons; watercolors; sketches; postcards; stereographs; souvenir albums; leaflets; and small broadsides. Organized into four main series: Subjects, Geographic, Socialist Party, and People. To allow for better housing, Negatives and Stereographs have been separated into their own series.
The images offer representations of the landscape, culture, and history of most of the southern United States, especially Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Maryland, North and South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia. Many images of France, Italy, Germany, Japan, China, and some African countries can also be found; a large number of other countries and geographic locations are represented by only a few images. Many political figures and notable personages are portrayed, both in portrait and in caricature; there are especially significant numbers of images of Eugene Debs, Socialist Party leader, and members of the Duke family of Durham, N.C. The history of Durham is also well-represented, in addition to other Southern cities and towns, including Raleigh N.C.
Civil War images are abundant, offering views of battles and scenes of devastation both rural and urban. Other conflicts are also depicted, including the American Revolutionary War, Spanish-American War, and there are some images from both World Wars. A significant group of items in the People Series pertains to African Americans, ranging from studio portraits to caricatures of individuals and groups of individuals; a smaller group of images features depictions of Native Americans. Finally, the Picture File is home to collections of many engravings and lithographs produced by the 19th century American companies Currier and Ives, L. Prang and Co., and Kurz and Allison; many of them commemorate military leaders or events.
United States -- History -- Pictorial works; Socialism -- United States -- History -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- History -- Pictorial works; Durham County (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; South Carolina -- History -- Pictorial works; Georgia -- History -- Pictorial works; Charleston (S.C.) -- History -- 19th century; Virginia -- History -- Pictorial works; African Americans -- Pictorial works; Native Americans -- Portraits; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Pictorial works; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Cities and towns -- Southern States -- Pictorial works; Southern States -- Photographs; Caricatures and cartoons; Postcards; Stereographs; Lithographs; Engravings (prints); Albumen prints; Negatives (photographs); Confederate States of America; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Clay family; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1809; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Socialist Party (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Kurz and Allison; Currier & Ives
- Subjects Series, 1800s-1950; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Items relating to a variety of subjects, including architecture, automobiles, fashion, political cartoons and caricatures, and military conflicts, particularly the American Civil War but also the Revolutionary, Spanish-American, and World Wars.
  - Advertising/Design, 1
    - "Landing of the Pilgrims on Plymouth Rock," advertisement for Plymouth Rock Pants, color lithograph (Box 56)
    - Cartoon narrative with child-like figures, illustrating successful salesmanship, English, by James R. Harrison, circa 1881, 6 color lithograph cards (Box 58, Folder M1820)
    - Charleston Consolidated Railway Co. Advertisement: Isle of Palms, Charleston, SC, late 1800s, lithograph (Oversize-folder 42)
    - Photographs of department store display windows for women's clothing, with commentary on design elements, 1940s, 10 black-and-white photographs (Box 58, Folder M1819)
  - American life and customs, 2
    - American bridal dress and veil (bride unidentified), undated, card photograph (Box 1, Folder M11)
    - American Issues Forum poster, 1976 (Oversize-folder 26)
    - Dining Hall, Joyce Kilmer C.C.C Camp No.148, 1900s, black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M23)
    - Ku Klux Klan robes, [1868], 1909, card photograph (Box 1, Folder M10)
      Drawing from a photograph made in 1868 by Federal soldiers who captured the costumes after a Ku Klux Klan parade.
    - Unidentified bride and groom, circa 1940s, black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M24)
    - Unidentified individuals, 1872 and 1800s, 20 card photographs and 2 tintypes (Box 1, Folder M12)
  - Architecture, 3
    - Farmhouse (American, unidentified), undated, black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M1)
    - Progress, American, undated, 4 photographs of engravings (Box 1, Folder M2)
      Transferred from the David E. Evans Papers. These pictures bear no formal title. They show the development of a farm from the time it was settled until it became a prosperous establishment.
    - Stechert portfolio of twelve engravings of famous European libraries, undated, 12 engravings (Box 1, Folder M4)
      Includes index of engravings.
    - Town house (American, unidentified) with four people, 1800s, card photograph (Box 1, Folder M3)
  - Arts and Trades, 4
    - Bloody Sentence of the Jews against Jesus Christ, the Savior of the World, 1867; black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 10)
      Note attached: "The original of this was found under a church in Vienna in Germany, cut upon a stone, and was brought to this country in 1782 by Joseph Kerner."
    - Chapelier, engraving (Box 59)
    - Intercepted Despatches, John Seymour Lucas, circa 1877, engraving (Box 1, Folder M5)
    - Landscape: The 'Weierhaus,' near Nuremberg, 20th c., black-and-white illustration (Box 1, Folder M5a)
      Photo reproduction of Durer original in the British Museum.
    - Madonna and an unidentified painting, Bartolome Esteban Murillo, undated, 2 card photographs (Box 1, Folder M6)
    - Married, 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Mineralogie et Metallurgie, Mercure, late 1700s?, engraving (Box 59)
    - Miroitier, Metteur au Teint, late 1700s?, engraving (Box 59)
    - Study for engraving of "The Prodigal Son," 20th c., black-and-white illustration (Box 1, Folder M5b)
    - The Rhinoceros, 20th c., black-and-white illustration (Box 1, Folder M5c)
    - Moby Dick illustration, 1976 (Oversize-folder 26)
    - Itinerant man with tri-cornered hat, scissors, and unidentified tool, 19th century?, black-and-white engraving (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Cartoons and Caricatures, 5
    - African American caricatures and stereotypes, approximately 1860s-1910s; 15 color lithographs (13 unique; 2 are copies) (Box 38)
      Currier and Ives
    - [Civil war political cartoons], 1861-1865, 52 engravings (Box 39)
      Published in "Fun Magazine," London.
    - A New Method of Macaroni making, as practised at Boston, undated, black-and-white lithograph (Box 56)
      H. R. Robinson Cartoons
    - A Pedlar and his Pack or the Desperate Effort, an Overbalance, circa 1826, political cartoon, color (Box 39)
      Depicts John Quincy Adams, Henry Clay, Daniel Webster carrying coffins; possibly in reference to Panama mission of 1826.
    - American Tobacco Co. Nos. 112-118, undated, 6 color illustrations and 6 slides (Box 39)
      The slides and six illustrations are copies of the items in the following entry.
    - An Unpublished Cartoon of Reconstruction Days in South Carolina - An Amateur Artist's Conception of Scott's Administration (1868-1872), 20th c., black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M8)
    - Benjamin Franklin Butler in the Civil War, 1861 and circa 1860s, 6 clippings and 1 engraving (Box 39)
    - British Warfare in 1812, 1837-38, undated, black-and-white lithograph (Box 56)
    - Field Marshall Count Suwarrow Romaniskoy, 1799, color etching (Box 55)
      J. Gillray Caricatures
    - Gin, Two-Penny and Tobacco, 1802, color illustration (Box 55)
      Giles Grinagain Cartoons
    - Guy Vaux discovered in his attempt to destroy the King and the house of Lords, 1791, color etching (Box 55)
    - Illustration by George Cruikshank, no known title, before 1878, color lithograph? (Box 59)
    - It's no Use a Knocking at the Doors, late 19th c.?, card photograph (Box 1, Folder M9)
    - Jefferson Davis, 1861, 1863, 1865 and circa 1860s, 5 engravings, 5 card photographs, 7 black-and-white illustrations, 2 color illustrations and 3 pamphlets (Box 39)
    - Satan Reproving Sin, undated, black-and-white lithograph (Box 56)
    - Secession and the Civil War, 1800s and 1770, 14 engravings and 1 color engraving (Box 39)
    - Taking a header, circa 1910, color illustration (Box 57)
      Re: Bicycles. Accompanied by printed poem.
    - The Baltimoreans going the whole Ass tail and all, undated, black-and-white lithograph (Box 56)
    - The Beauties of Boswell, 1942, Rawlandson, Thomas cartoonist, album (Box 39)
      20th century reproductions of nine original color cartoons printed in 1786. Includes an introduction.
    - The Explanation, 1798, color etching (Box 55)
    - The would-be Mayor attempting to quell a riot, undated, black-and-white lithograph (Box 56)
    - U.S. Politics 1831-1841, 1831-circa 1841, 15 engravings and 2 color engravings (Box 39)
  - Children
    - Boy with lute / In the cabinet at Houghton..., 1780, Black-and-white engraving, by Picot (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Civil War, American, 6
    - [Gettysburg] "Notes on the Invasion of Maryland and Pennsylvania and The Battle of Gettysburg with Explanatory Map and Souvenir Album," circa 1888, souvenir album (Box 2, Folder M60)
      Map missing; contains about 50 small images, seem to be ink drawings taken from postcards or photographs; some are reproductions of Paul Philippoteaux paintings. Handle with care; bindings fragile.
    - A Scouting Party by Forbes, 1877, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Action Between the Kearsarge and Alabama. (Rescue of the crew of the Alabama by the Deerhound), undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M28)
    - Action of the Gunboats at Memphis, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M29)
      From the original painting by Chappel.
    - Admiral Farragut's Fleet Engaging the Rebel Batteries at Port Hudson, March 14th 1863, circa 1863, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Admiral Porter's Fleet Running the Rebel Blockade of the Mississippi at Vicksburg, April 16th 1863, circa 1863, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - After the Battle. 'Bloody Lane' Antietam, 1889 Aug. 28, card photograph (Box 38)
      Copy of a painting by Capt. James Hope.
    - Andersonville Stockade, 1903, color illustration (Oversize-folder 9)
    - Antietam, 1887, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
      L. Prang and Co.
    - Appearance of Fort Sumter on Sunday Afternoon August 23d 1863, undated, lithograph (Box 47)
      Sketched from the 'Beacon House' on Morris Island. "Drawn from nature by W.T. Crone."
    - Assault on Fort Sanders, 1891, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
      Kurz and Allison
    - Attack at Rocky Face Ridge, Ga., undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M33)
    - Attack of the Rebels upon our Gun Boats in Galveston Harbor, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M31)
    - Attack on Fredericksburgh - Dec. 1862, 1862, Dec. 13, engraving (Box 1, Folder M30)
    - Attack Upon Roanoke Island - Landing of the Troops, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M32)
    - Awaiting the Attack by Forbes, 1877, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Battle at Wilson's Creek, Mo., undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M44)
    - Battle of Antietam, 1887, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Battle of Ball's Bluff, Va. - Rescuing the body of Brig. Gen. Baker, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M34)
    - Battle of Bull Run - July 1861 (Gen. Blenker's Brigade covering the retreat), undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M35)
    - Battle of Bull Run, July 21st, 1861, 1861, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Battle of Cedar Creek, 1890, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Champion Hill, 1887, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Chicamauga - Lt. Van Pelt Defending his Battery, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M36)
    - Battle of Corinth, 1891, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Corinth, Miss. Oct. 4th 1862, 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
      From the Currier and Ives Collection.
    - Battle of Corinth, Miss. Oct. 4th 1862, 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Battle of Fort Donelson, 1887, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Franklin, 1891, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Gettysburg, 1887, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Battle of Keneshaw Mountain, 1888, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Battle of Lookout Mountain, "Ropers Rock Showing First Union Troops Scaling Cliffs - Nov 25th 1863," undated, black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M38)
      Given by Mrs. I. E. Gray, Durham, NC.
    - Battle of Lookout Mountain, 1889, color illustration (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Battle of Lookout Mountain, Ga., undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M37)
    - Battle of Malvern Hill, Va. - U.S. Gun Boats on James River Covering the Retreat, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M39)
    - Battle of Mill Spring, Ky., Jan. 19th 1862, circa 1863, lithograph (Box CUR1)
      Currier and Ives Lithographs
    - Battle of Missionary Ridge, 1863, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 6)
      Image is glued to cardboard, flaking off in places.
    - Battle of Murfreesboro - Capture of a Confederate Flag, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M40)
    - Battle of New Bern, N.C. March 14th 1862, 1862, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Battle of Olustee, Florida, 1894, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Battle of Pea Ridge, Arkansas, March 8 1862, 1862, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Battle of Resaca, 1889, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Battle of Rich Mountain, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M42)
    - Battle of Shiloh, 1888, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Battle of Shiloh, Tenn. - Charge of General Grant, undated, 2 engravings (Box 1, Folder M43)
      Duplicate copy included.
    - Battle of Spottsylvania, 1887, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Battle of the Rams, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M41)
    - Battle of Williamsburg, 1893, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Battle of Wilson Creek, 1893, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Bird's Eye View of Confederate Prison Pen - at Salisbury, N.C. - Taken in 1864, undated, black-and-white photograph (Box 1, Folder M45)
      Includes brief notes specifying different parts of the prison.
    - Birds Eye View of Confederate Prison Pen at Salisbury, NC, 1864, color engraving (Oversize-folder 15)
    - Bombardment and Capture of Fredericksburg, VA, 1862, color lithograph (Box 56)
      Currier and Ives.
    - Bombardment and Capture of the Forts at Hatteras Inlet, N.C. by the U.S. Fleet Under Commodore Stringham and the Forces Under General Butler, Aug. 27 1861, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Bombardment of Fort Hatteras, North Carolina, August 29th 1861..., undated, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Bombardment of Fort Pulaski, Cockspur Island, Geo...., 1862, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Bombardment of Fort Sumter, Charleston Harbor, 12th and 13th of April, 1861, circa 1862, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Bombardment of Forts Hatteras and Clark by the US fleet under the command of Silas H. Stringham on the 28th and 29th of August 1861, 1864, color engraving (Oversize-folder 15)
    - Bombardment of Island no. 10 - Gun and Mortar Boats on the Mississippi, undated, engraving (Box 1, Folder M46)
    - Bombardment of Port Royal, S.C. - Transport Fleet in the Distance, undated, 2 engravings (Box 1, Folder M47)
      Includes names of depicted ships and forts. Duplicate copy included.
    - Brilliant Naval Victory on the Mississippi River, Near Fort Wright, May 10th 1862, 1862, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Camp Chesebrough, Baltimore, Md. -- 1st Reg. Connecticut Cavalry, 1863, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Camp of the 37th Mass. Vol's. Near Brandy Station Va., 1800s, lithograph (Box 38)
      Negative available.
    - Camp Oliver 25th Mass. V. Infantry, New Berne, N.C. 1862, undated, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Camp Tilden Winter Quarters of 16th Maine Regiment Mar. 5, 1864, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 9)
    - Camp Washburn, 10th Maine Regiment, Col. George L. Beal, 1861, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 49)
    - Campbell U.S. Genl. Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1864, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Capture of Fort Donelson, Tenn. - Charge of Gen. Smith's Division, undated, engraving (Box 2, Folder M48)
    - Capture of Fort Fisher, 1890, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Capture of New Orleans -- The Fleet Passing Forts on the Mississippi, undated, engraving (Box 2, Folder M49)
      Includes names of depicted ships.
    - Capture of the Works at Petersburg, undated, engraving (Box 2, Folder M50)
    - Carver Barracks, Washington D.C., 1864, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Castle Thunder, Richmond, Looking Up Carey Street, 1865 Apr. 7, A. Gardner, photographer, card photograph (Box 2, Folder M51)
    - Cliffburne Hospital, Washington D.C., 1862, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Catholic Convent, S.E. Corner Blanding and Main Street -- Where Tapp's Store is Now, black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
      May be 19th c. reproductions of card photographs.
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Christ Episcopal Church, S.E. Corner of Blanding and Marion Streets, black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Freight Depot of S.C.R.R. - Later Rebuilt, black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Lutheran Church (Ebenezer), black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Main Street from State House Grounds, black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
    - Columbia After Sherman's Visit: Washington Street M.E. Church, black-and-white photograph (Box 2, Folder M52)
    - Come and Join Us Brothers, 1863, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Confederate flags and seals, undated, 5 colored and uncolored paper prints (Box 2, Folder M53)
      From the Chas E. Jones Papers scrapbook.
    - Confederate monument, Augusta, Ga., undated, 4 colored and uncolored paper prints (Box 2, Folder M54)
      Affixed to a single scrapbook page. From the Chas E. Jones Papers scrapbook.
    - Death of General Lyon, 1862, lithograph (Box CUR2)
    - Design for Monument to Gen. E. Kirby Smith, Sewanee, Tenn., undated, 3 uncolored paper prints (Box 2, Folder M55)
    - Edward Everett, Our Next Vice President, [1860], color lithograph (Box 38)
      From the Currier and Ives Collection. Contains possibly authentic signature.
    - Experience of the 9th Mass. Battery at Gettysburg, Penn., July, 1863, undated, card photograph (Box 2, Folder M56)
    - First Naval Combat Between Iron Vessels, 1862 Mar. 9, engraving (Box 2, Folder M57)
    - Fort Federal Hill, Baltimore MD, 1862, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 47)
    - Fort McAllister, 1865, engraving (Box 2, Folder M58)
      Taken from The Story of the Great March. From The Diary of a Staff Officer, by Brevet Major George Wards Nichols, aide-de-camp to General Sherman, Harper and Bros., New York, 1865; transferred from the Marmaduke Floyd Collection.
    - Fort Pennsylvania, Head Quarters of the 113th Regt. N.Y.S.V. -- Col. O. L. Morricee, Comm., 1862, lithograph (Box 50)
    - Fort Pickens, Pensacola Harbor, Florida, 1860s, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Fort Pillow Massacre, 1892, color illustration (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Fort Sumter 'Repossessed' by the Union, Feb. 18, 1865, undated, lithograph (Box 2, Folder M59)
    - Fort Sumter. Charleston Harbor, S.C., 1860s, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Freedom to the Slaves, 1800s, lithograph (Box 38)
    - General Philip Kearney, circa 1863, lithograph (Box CUR3)
    - General Sherman On the March to the Sea, 1868, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 35)
    - General Stoneman's Great Cavalry Raid, May 1863, 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - German Artillery Near Washington, 1861, black-and-white photo (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Gettysburg Battlefield, 1863, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 31)
      Bird's-eye view, shows topography and troop placements. Contains reproduction of Gen. Meade's approval of the map. Labeled "proof" in one corner.
    - Gettysburg. Repulse of Longstreet's Assault, 1905, black-and-white lithograph (Oversize-folder 31)
    - Glorious Charge of Hancock's Division 2nd of the Army of the Potomac, 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Grand Gulf City. Return of the 4th Wis. and 6th Mich. Volunteers..., 1800s, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - Hold the Fort, 1876, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 9)
      Thomas Nast cartoon, signed by the artist. Also contains black-and-white photo of the printed cartoon, dated 1876.
    - Home From the War, 1862, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Home on a Furlough, 1864, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 57)
    - Hon. John Bell, 'Our Next President,' 1860, color lithograph (Box 38)
    - In Commemoration of the glorious victories of the 3rd an 9th of April 1864, Richmond Virginia, undated, color lithograph (Box 55)
    - In Memoriam, 1867, engraving (Box 38)
    - Inauguration of Jefferson Davis, 1878, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 51)
    - Interior of Fort Sumter During the Bombardment, April 12th 1861, 1861, color lithograph (Box 59)
    - Jarvis U.S. General Hospital, Baltimore MD, 1864, color lithograph (Oversize-folder 47)
    - Just in Time by Forbes, 1877, black-and-white engraving (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Landing of Troops on Roanoke Island -- Burnside Expedition, 1862, engraving (Box 2, Folder M61)
    - Last of the Alabama, Respectfully Inscribed to the crew of the Kearsarge, Commodore Winslow's Grand Victory March, 1864, color lithograph (Box 56)
    - Last Wooden Navy Battle, 1907, color engraving (Oversize-folder 6)
      Merrimac (Virginia) [Ironclad] vs USS Cumberland and USS Congress.
    - Libbey Prison, Richmond, Va., 1865 Apr. 6, A. Gardner, photographer, 2 card photographs (Box 2, Folder M62)
    - Lieut. Gen. N. B. Forrest, 1800s, engraving (Box 38)